Department of Special Collections, Hesburgh Libraries of Notre Dame
American Colonial Currency Collection
- New York CurrencyNew York, New YorkNew YorkApril 20, 1756, NY 04/20/56; James Parker;
  - Ten Pounds8185 8185, 203; Signers: John Van der Spiegel, John Cruger and Robert R. Livingston; Size: 57 x 99 mm (border dimensions: 56 x 97mm; the back is blank).
    Signed and numbered in brown ink. In the top center of the bill there is a picture of two one pound weights with a Roman numeral 'V' superimposed on each. The seal of the City of New York appears on the right front. Newman states this issue is the first to include the punctuation in the word "It's" in the counterfeiting warning. Some denominations, as the 20s, have an apostrophe in the word "It's" (pictured in Newman), while our example, like the £10 notes of most other emissions, lacks the apostrophe. On the back are some handwritten annotations: the initials TB are upside down right of center, the initials NM are found in a very light ink near the upper border and to the left, while a darker M is to the right and finally in the upper right corner in a light brown ink J. R. Wr[ight] ? This note has an annotated back.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 08/23/97, lot 463.
- New York Currency April 15, 1758New York, New YorkNew YorkApril 15, 1758, NY 04/15/58; James Parker;
  An emission of ฃ100,000 in legal tender bills of credit to finance the second expedition to Crown Point and to be redeemed by November 1768. Engraved border cuts with the seal of the City of New York. Printed by James Parker in New York City with a blank back made from coarse dark paper. Denominations issued: ฃ5 and ฃ10.
  - Ten Pounds8887 8887, 204; Signers: David Van Horne, Peter Livingston, Henry Cuyler, Jr.; Size: 57 x 98 mm (border dimensions: 54 x 94mm; the back is blank).
    Signed and numbered in brown ink. In the top center of the bill there is a picture of two one pound weights with a Roman numeral 'V' superimposed on each. The seal of the City of New York appears on the right front. This is the last issue in this series of bills with the serial numbers placed on the side margin. Also, this is the only emission in the series that frames the initial letter with an ornamental design. The back is blank.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 04/20/96, lot 507.
- New York Currency April 2, 1759New York, New YorkNew YorkApril 2, 1759, NY 04.02.59; William Weyman;
  An emission of ฃ100,000 in legal tender bills of credit. Engraved border cuts with the seal of the City of New York. Printed by William Weyman in New York City on thin paper. Denominations issued: ฃ2, ฃ5 and ฃ10.
  - Five Pounds6500 6500, 205; Signers: Nathaniel Marston, Andrew Barclay, John Morin Scot; Size: 61 x 102 mm (border dimensions: 57 x 94mm; the back is blank).
    Signed and numbered in brown ink. In the top center of the bill there is a picture of a pound weight with a Roman numeral 'V' superimposed. The seal of the City of New York appears on the right front. Note that the denomination under the seal is printed backwards V £:. This is the first issue in this series of bills with the serial numbers placed at the top. The back is blank.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 04/20/96, lot 508.
  - Two Pounds11559 11559, 515; Signers: Nathaniel Marston, Lawrence Reade, Andrew Barclay
    Signed and numbered in brown ink. In the top center of the bill there is a picture of two pound weights, indicating the denomination of the note.
    EAHA Mail Bid Auction, lot #2071, 12/01/07. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- New York Currency April 21, 1760New York, New YorkNew YorkApril 21, 1760, NY 04/21/60; William Weyman;
  An emission of ฃ60,000 in legal tender bills of credit. Printed by William Weyman in New York City. The text follows that of the previous emission of April 2, 1759 while the border cuts follow those of the February 16, 1756 and April 20, 1756 issues. The seal of the city of New York is based on engravings made by Charles Le Roux for the November 15, 1734 issue and the border cuts are based on cut Le Roux made for the December 10, 1737 issue. This was the last in a series of 13 similar issues which started in December of 1737. Denominations issued were ฃ2, ฃ5 and ฃ10.
  - Five Pounds1548 1548, 206; Signers: Elias Des Brosses, John Van Horne, John Bogert, Jr.; Size: 56 x 92 mm (outside edges of front border design trimmed--inside border dimensions: 48 x 81mm; the back is blank).
    Signed and numbered in brown ink. In the top center of the bill there is a picture of a pound weight with a Roman numeral 'V' superimposed. The seal of the City of New York appears on the right front. Handwritten annotation "Wi." on back. This note has an annotated back.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 1/13/96, lot 412.
- New York Currency February 16, 1771New York, New YorkNew YorkFebruary 16, 1771, NY 02/16/71; Hugh Gaine;
  An emission of ฃ120,000 in bills of credit receivable for taxes. Printed by Hugh Gaine in New York City on thin laid paper. The new decorative top border cut with Britannia, an Indian, and Commerce as well as the left border cut and the Arms of New York City were made by Elisha Gallaudet of New York City. Printed by Hugh Gaine on thin laid paper. There was extensive counterfeiting of this issue. Denomination issued were: 5s, 10s, ฃ1. ฃ2, ฃ3, ฃ5 and ฃ10.
  - Two Pounds6295 6295, 207; Signers: Theophylact Bache, Samuel Verplanck, A. Lott.; Size: 67 x 98 mm (front border design: 65 x 96mm; back blank).
    First signature in a light red ink, the second is in black and the third is in a light brown ink. The seal of the City of New York appears on front right. At the top is the seated Britannia in a roundel with an Indian holding a bow and arrows and the new world to the right, while to the left is a figure of Commerce seated on a barrel and holding a lyre with ships behind her. There are four varieties of this bill in Newman our example is Newman's variety d having 8-pointed stars along the bottom. Handwritten annotations on back read "John Straker" on the lower right and "William Morris" on the left edge. This note has an annotated back.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 12/2/95, lot 484.
  - Three Pounds63961 63961, 208; Signers: Theophylact Bache, Samuel Verplanck, A. Lott; Size: 66 x 99mm (front border design: 66 x 98mm; back blank).
    The seal of the City of New York appears on front right. At the top is the seated Britannia in a roundel with an Indian holding a bow and arrows and the new world to the right, while to the left is a figure of Commerce seated on a barrel and holding a lyre with ships behind her. In the paper is the right half of a circular watermark (45mm) with a G to the right edge. The back is blank.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EAHA mail bid auction of 1/17/98, lot 347.
  - Ten Pounds27236 27236, 209; Signers: Samuel Verplanck, Theophylact Bache, A. Lott.; Size: 69 x 100 mm (front border design: 65 x 96mm; back blank).
    First and third signatures in brown ink and the second signature and the serial number in red ink. The seal of the City of New York appears on front right. At the top is the seated Britannia in a roundel with an Indian holding a bow and arrows and the new world to the right, while to the left is a figure of Commerce seated on a barrel and holding a lyre with ships behind her. The back is blank.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 12/2/95 Lot 484.
- New York Currency August 25, 1774New York, New YorkNew YorkAugust 25, 1774, NY 08/25/74; Hugh Gaine; Elisha Gallaudet
  An emission of ฃ2,400 in promissory notes issued by the City of New York, known as the first of four "Water Works" issues. This is the first paper currency emitted by a city in colonial America. All previous general emissions had been issued by the authority of a colony. Within a year Albany had issued currency (on June 22, 1775) and a second "Water Works" emission had been issued. Later, in 1786 Charleston, S.C. issued currency, then during the copper panic of the 1790's several cities issued small denomination bills. However, it should be remembered that privately printed bank and merchant notes date back much earlier as the notes Benjamin Franklin printed in June of 1729 for the Philadelphia shopkeeper Evan Morgan. A significant number of private issues continue throughout the colonial and confederation periods. This issue is known as the Water Works Issue because the back of each note has an engraving of a steam powered water pump proposed by the engineer Christopher Colles. The front of the bills has an engraved top border cut while the other three borders are typeset. In this series the first emission and part of the second water works emission have backs with white paper. A large portion of the second emission and all of the third and fourth emissions have white paper on the front but a dark coarse paper on the back of the notes. The plates were engraved by Elisha Gallaudet, who also cut the borders and devices for the Continental Congress "fugio" denominations of February 17, 1776 and cut the dies for the so called "1776 Continental Congress Dollar." The Water Works emissions were printed by Hugh Gaine in New York City with red and black inks on the face and black ink on the back. Notes were signed and numbered in brown and black inks. Denominations issued in this emission were: 1s, 2s, 4s and 8s. These denominations had not been issued in the colony of New York since November 16, 1726.
  August 25, 1774- NYC
  - One Shilling2691 2691, 210; Signers: Whitehead Hicks, J. Watts, Jr.; Size: 58 x 95 mm (front border design: 55 x 91mm; back border design: 53 x 89mm).
    First signature and numbering in light brown and second signature in black ink. The reverse is on white paper.
    EANA mail bid auction 11/16/96 Lot 637. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- New York Currency August 2, 1775New York, New YorkNew YorkAugust 2, 1775, NY 08/02/75; Hugh Gaine; Elisha Gallaudet
  An emission of ฃ2,500 in promissory notes from New York City, called the second Water Works issue. (The first issue, which was the first paper currency issued by an individual city, was from August 25, 1774). Printed by Hugh Gaine with red and black on the front and black on the back. The front has a border cut at the top but the other borders are type set. The cut is by Elisha Gallaudet who also did the illustration on the back of a steam operated water pump proposed by Christopher Colles. The back of these bills has a darker and coarser paper than the front. A 1s note was authorized but never issued. Denominations issued were: 2s, 4s and 8s.
  August 2, 1775- NYC
  - Eight Shillings5900 5900, 211; Signers: Whitehead Hicks, George Brewerton.; Size: 60 x 98 mm (front border design: 54 x 92mm; back border design: 52 x 84mm).
    First signature and numbering in dark brown and second signature in light brown ink.
    EANA mail bid auction 1/13/96 Lot 414. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- New York Currency September 2, 1775New York, New YorkNew YorkSeptember 2, 1775, NY 09/02/75; John Holt;
  An emission of $112,500 (ฃ45,000) in legal tender bills of credit payable in Spanish milled dollars or the same value in gold or silver. Half of the bills were to be due on March 1, 1776 and the rest on March 1, 1777, but with both due dates extended one year. This issue, the first New York issue denominated in dollars, has newly engraved borders, Includes city arms on the obverse, and on the reverse, emblem cuts and mottoes derived from an emblem book by J. C. Weigels. Printed by John Holt of New York City on thick paper. Originally there were three signers but by a resolution of December 16, 1775 this was reduced to two. Denominations issued were: $1/2, $1, $2, $3, $5 and $10.
  - One Dollar2057 2057, 212; Signers: William Denning (faded brown ink), Robert Ray.; Size: 64 x 107 mm (front border dimensions: 64 x 105mm; back border dimensions: 63 (trimmed) x 105).
    Numbered in black ink. The first signature is in reddish-brown ink, the second in black. Seal of the City of New York on front right. The emblem on the back depicts a sheaf of wheat with the motto: "Acervus e parvis grandis" (A massive stack from small things).
    EANA mail bid auction 12/2/95 Lot 485. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Ten Dollar2760 2760, 213; Signers: Anthony L. Bleecker, another in red is faded.; Size: 64 x 109 mm (front border dimensions: 67 x 105mm; back border dimensions: 67 x 104).
    Number and first signature in very faded red ink; second in brown ink. Seal of the City of New York on front right. In the upper border cut is a sheaf of wheat and a ship. The emblem on the back depicts an elephant with the motto: "Par viribus virtus" (Virtue is equal to strength).
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 Lot 513. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- New York January 6, 1776New York, New YorkNew YorkJanuary 6, 1776, NY 01/06/76; Hugh Gaine;
  An emission of ฃ2,750 in promissory notes issued by the City of New York, known as the third of four "Water Works" issues. The numeral 3 over the initial T on the face of the notes indicates this was the third issue. The series is known as the Water Works issues because the back of each note has an engraving of a steam powered water pump proposed by the engineer Christopher Colles. The front of the bills has an engraved top border cut while the other three borders are typeset. The plates for these designs were engraved by Elisha Gallaudet, who also cut the borders and devices for the Continental Congress "fugio" denominations of February 17, 1776 and cut the dies for the so called "1776 Continental Congress Dollar." The Water Works emission was printed by Hugh Gaine in New York City with red and black inks on the face and black ink on the back. A coarse dark paper was used on the back of all denominations in this issue. Signed and numbered in brown and black inks. Denominations issued were: 2s, 4s and 8s.
  January 6, 1776- NYC
  - Four Shillings451 451, 214; Signers: N. Bayard, John H. Cruger.; Size: 56 x 94 mm (front border design: 55 x 91mm; back border design: 52 x 90mm).
    Numbering and signatures in light brown. The second signature is quite faded.
    EANA mail bid auction 11/16/96 Lot 641. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- New York Currency February 17, 1776Albany, New YorkNew YorkFebruary 17, 1776, NY 02/17/76; ;
  This is the second issue of personal promissory notes for the Committee of Correspondence of the City and County of Albany (the first issue was on June 22, 1755). The bills, payable in Continental Currency, were denominated in fractions of a Spanish milled dollar and were type set with a top border cut. Denominations issued were: 1s (equal to $1/8), 1s6d (equal to $1/6), 2s (equal to $1/4), 4s (equal to $1/2) and 5s (equal to $5/8).
  February 17, 1776- Albany
  - Two Shillings4405 4405, 215; Signers: Jacob Cuyler, John T. Beeckman (in red ink, faded); Size: 54 x 86 mm (front border design: 51 x 85mm; back blank).
    Numbered in black ink; first signature in black, second in red. The back is blank.
    EANA mail bid auction 1/13/96 Lot 418. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- New York Currency March 5, 1776New York, New YorkNew YorkMarch 5, 1776, NY 03/05/76; Samuel Loudon;
  An emission of ฃ55,000 ($137,000) in legal tender bills of credit payable in Spanish milled dollars with an additional 6,000 $1/8 bills included on August 13, 1776. This issue was redeemable in three sections by March 1 of 1779, 1780 or 1781. Similar to the issue of September 2, 1775 with additional fractional denominations. Three engraved border cuts and the state arms on the front and border cuts with an emblem and motto on the back. The mottos and emblems come from the emblem book of J.C. Weigles. Printed by Samuel Loudon on thick paper. Denominations issued were: $1/8 (1s), $1/6 (1s4d), $1/4 (2s), $1/3 (2s8d), $1/2, $2/3 (5s4d), $1, $2, $3, $5 and $10.
  - Two-Thirds Dollar24033 24033, 217; Signers: Cornelius Ray, William Heyer.; Size: not available.
    This bill is denominated as $2/3 and as 5s4d. Seal of the City of New York on front right. According to Newman the emblem on the back depicts an eagle with the motto: "Fortis a forte" (Strength comes from strength). No reproduction of the back was available.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 20, 1996, lot 517.
  - One Third Dollar16390 16390, 216; Signers: John H. Thompson, Charles Duryee.; Size: 65 x 105 mm (front border dimensions: 59 x 97 mm; back border dimensions: 58 x 97 mm).
    This bill is denominated as $1/3 and as 2s8d. According to Newman, bills were signed by Jacob K. Duryee but this examples appears to have Charles Duryee. Seal of the City of New York on front right. The emblem on the back depicts three linked wreaths, probably a military decoration, with the motto: "His ornari aut mori" (To be decorated with these or to die).
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 Lot 516. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - One Dollar4177 4177, 218; Cornelius Ray, William Heyer (very light); Size: 66.5 x 109 mm (front border dimensions: 62 x 104 mm; back border dimensions: 62 x 105 mm).
    First signature and numbering in brown ink, second signature very faded in red. Seal of the City of New York on front right. The emblem on the back depicts a bundle of wheat with the moto "Acervus e parvis Grandis" (Great accumulation from small things). Printed by Samuel Loudon in New York.
    EANA mail bid auction 1/18/97 Lot 326. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- New York Currency, March 5, 1776New York, New YorkNew YorkMarch 5, 1776, NY 03/05/76; Hugh Gaine; Elisha Gallaudet
  An emission of ฃ2,000 in promissory notes from New York City, called the fourth Water Works issue. (The first issue, which was the first paper currency issued by an individual city, was from August 25, 1774). Note the numeral 4 over the initial T indicating the fourth issue. This code was only used in the third and fourth issues. In the same style as the previous issues with a white paper on the front and a darker and coarser paper on the back. Printed by Hugh Gaine with red and black on the front and black on the back, The front had a border cut at the top but the other borders are type set. The cut is by Elisha Gallaudet who also did the illustration on the back of a steam operated water pump proposed by Christopher Colles. Denominations issued were: 4s and 8s.
  March 5, 1776- NYC
  - Four Shillings1118 1118, 220; Signers: Benjamin Bragge.; Size: 89 x 69 mm (front border design: 88 x 68mm; back border design: 52 x 65mm).
    Signed and numbered in brown ink. A small 4 over the 'T' in "THIS" indiactes this is the fourth Water Works issue.
- New York Currency August 13, 1776New York, New YorkNew YorkAugust 13, 1776, NY 08.13.76; Samuel Loudon;
  An emission of $500,000 (ฃ200,000) in legal tender bills of credit payable in Spanish milled dollars or the same value in gold or silver. This issue contains similar border cuts and the same emblems and mottos as on the Colony of New York March 5, 1776, emission (not to be confused with the NYC emission of the same date). However, the $1/16, which was not in the earlier emission, is without an emblem. As on previous issues the emblem devices derive from a book of emblems by J. C. Weigels. Printed by Samuel Loudon of New York City on thick paper. Following the practice on contemporary Continental Currency, no one dollar denomination was issued, because of the anticipated minting of one dollar Continental Currency coins. Denominations issued were: $1/16 (6d), $1/8 (1s), $1/4 (2s), $1/2 (4s), $2, $3, $5 and $10.
  - Three Dollars15611 15611, 221; Signers: Benjamin Newkerk, Alexander Webster.; Size: 69 x 114 mm (front border design: 62 x 106mm; back border design: 62 x 106mm).
    Signed and numbered in black ink. Seal of City of New York on front right. On the back right there is an emblem of the Ten Commandments with the motto: "Lex regit, arma tuenter" (Law rules, weapons protect).
    EANA mail bid auction 12/02/95 lot 487. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- New York Currency, February 20, 1790New York, New YorkNew YorkFebruary 20, 1790, NY 02/20/90; Hugh Gaine;
  An emission of ฃ9,660 in small change notes issued by Common Council of the City of New York with the printed signature of the city treasurer Daniel Phoenix. Printed by Hugh Gaine in New York City. Once worn out notes were redeemed by the city they were burned. On April 22, 1790, because of the discovery of counterfeits (made in London), the entire issue was called in for redemption by June 1, 1790. Several communities and institutions issued small change notes following the copper panic of 1789, when the price of copper was devalued and few people would accept copper coins at their usual rates. Denominations issued were: 1d, 2d and 3d.
  February 20, 1790- NYC
  - Three Pence, 222; Signer: Daniel Phoenix (typset).; Size: not available
    Typeset signature of the city treasurer on the front. Image of the back is not available. The typeset back includes the statement the bill was printed by H. Gaine, New York.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 20, 1996, lot 519.
  - One Pence, 517; Signer: Daniel Phoenix (typset).
    Typeset signature of the city treasurer on the front. The typeset back includes the statement the bill was printed by H. Gaine, New York.
- New York Currency August 28, 1792New YorkAugust 28, 1792, NY 08/28/92; ;
  In July 1789 the public lost confidence in the lightweight copper coinage then in circulation and their value plummeted. Earlier 14 coppers were valued at a shilling but during the height of the panic it took 60 coppers to equal a shilling (if you could find someone willing to take the coppers!). In response to this "copper panic" municipalities, banks and churches printed their own small change notes. This is an example of Church money issued by the trustees of the Presbyterian Congregational Church of Troy, New York in Rensselaer County. This was done so the church would not be "stuck" with worthless coppers. One would purchase these notes at the church using silver coins or higher denomination currency at what had been the standard rate (say 14d to the shilling), then one could give their weekly contribution to the church (of one or two pence) without resorting to the worthless coppers. The notes were typeset by C.R. and G. Webster of Albany. At first these notes were signed by Morgan as treasurer while later notes were signed by B. Gorton as treasurer. Denominations issued were: 1d, 2d, 3d and 4d.
  August 28, 1792- First Presbyterian Church, Troy
  - One Penny, 223; Signer: Ephraim Morgan, Treasurer; Size: 46 x 75mm (front border dimensions: 42 x 70.5mm; back border dimensions: 43 x 71mm).
    At first these notes were signed by Morgan as treasurer while later notes were signed by B. Gorton.
    Purchased throught the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. auction of January 18, 1997, lot 329.